<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Health on digikar's microblog</title><link>https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/tags/health/</link><description>Recent content in Health on digikar's microblog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 23:19:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Extra extra protein and supplements!</title><link>https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/p/protein-supplement-safety/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 23:19:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/p/protein-supplement-safety/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some months ago, a friend recommended me the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/@Viva-Longevity" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Viva Longevity&lt;/a&gt; channel, and I occasionally watch it during brunch and dinner times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One particular video was about &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3LDe3k6lyac" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;protein obsession&lt;/a&gt;. I came across &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/health/lead-protein-powders-shakes-9.6941833" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;another article by CBC Canada&lt;/a&gt; on a similar topic today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, if I recall correctly, at least in US (and Canada too), &lt;em&gt;extra protein&lt;/em&gt; products (and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G8LG0OY3Izs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;supplements too&lt;/a&gt;!) are not regulated as well as medicines. That means, they arrive in the market without the stringent safety standards that medicines are subject to. They may be taken off the market in retrospect &lt;em&gt;once they are proven unsafe&lt;/em&gt;. From the company&amp;rsquo;s perspective, this allows them to make profits against the health hazards they put up consumers against. This forms yet another example of crony-capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, consume a healthy balanced diet focusing on unprocessed or minimally processed food. Think twice about supplements or other products sourced from industrial non-natural origins. When necessary, consult your doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>