<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Waste on digikar's microblog</title><link>https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/tags/waste/</link><description>Recent content in Waste on digikar's microblog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 09:03:55 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/tags/waste/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Taking Consumerism out of Halloween to make it Sustainable</title><link>https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/p/halloween-2025/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 09:03:55 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://digikar99.github.io/microblog/p/halloween-2025/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today is yet another day humans will celebrate something with one-off products. Not bothering what happens to the products after they are used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They go the waste, right? Or may be you recycle them? And then, they &lt;em&gt;eventually&lt;/em&gt; go to the waste, right? Right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you you know that the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/dec/09/human-made-materials-now-outweigh-earths-entire-biomass-study" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;amount of plastic is greater than all land animals and marine animals combined&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, plastic has become unavoidable. Yet, we can reduce single-purpose plastics as far as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
But how do I celebrate without dressing up?
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises two questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How was Halloween celebrated historically?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I still do a kinda-modern celebration without creating waste?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is an interesting question. A quick read at &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halloween" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; tells us &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wearing costumes and playing pranks at Halloween did not spread to England until the 20th century.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; Roughly, consumerism is a very recent century or two old phenomena compared to the human history of several thousand years. &lt;a class="link" href="https://animalarchaeology.com/2018/10/31/terror-and-tradition-over-time-a-look-at-the-material-culture-of-halloween/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; might be a nice read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t know what exactly a &lt;em&gt;traditional Halloween celebration&lt;/em&gt; looks like? I&amp;rsquo;m told I should visit rural or semi-urban areas of Europe to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s some nice &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.wastemanaged.co.uk/our-news/halloween/halloween-waste/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;waste statistics on Modern Halloween&lt;/a&gt; by WasteManaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the second question, there are plenty of guides once you start searching, for example, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/monicasanders/2025/10/27/5-ways-to-have-a-sustainable-spooky-season/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;this article by Forbes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Wish you all the best to a guilt-free celebration!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: If you created waste this year, that&amp;rsquo;s something to keep in mind for the upcoming celebrations! Be it Christmas, New Year, or the next Halloween! Or any other festivals you celebrate!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>